Lafayette mss., 1572-1939 LMC 2326
Lilly Library
- Manuscripts
  - Chronological
    - Alexander MacDonald, Duc d'Tarenti to Citoyen Bouchard, 1800, October 19; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Princess Amelia to Lady Neale and Duke of York (her brother), 1800, November 29; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 35)
      "Princess Amelia, 1783-1810, thirteenth child of George III and Charlotte Sophia. The top letter is addressed to Lady Neale; the letter at bottom is to her brother Duke of York."
    - Lafayette to Masclet - He (Lafayette) has decided not to accept any diplomatic post in America, but hopes to make private visits there - "If I should arrive in any other but an American uniform I should find myself as embarrassed and shame-faced as a savage who wear pants", 1800, November 23; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Pierre du Ponceau to William Young, 1800, December 3; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 35)
      "Pierre du Ponceau (1760-1844) when at the home of Beaumarchais in Paris met von Steuben who was about to start for America, and an English speaking and writing secretary being needed, they sailed together, arriving at Portsmouth, N.H. December 1, 1777. They journeyed to York, PA to be presented to Congress and at Steuben's request du Ponceau was made a Captain. In the winter of 1777, du Ponceau was at Valley Forge with General Washington, and when Steuben became a Major-General, du Ponceau became his aide-de-camp, with the rank of Major. He started South with Steuben, but failing health compelled him to return to Philadelphia, where he remained after the war, entered the Law and made considerable of a reputation. President Jefferson offered him the post of Chief Justice of the Territory of Louisiana, but it was declined."
    - John Anderson - Receipt to Lawrence Lewis, Acting Executor of the Estate of George Washington, for payment "of hire as Distiller at Mt. Vernon Distillery", 1801, January 17; ADS (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette does not wish to consider any diplomatic appointments to United States - Mentions Adams, Jefferson, Hamilton, Pinckney and Bushrod Washington, 1801, January 25; ADS (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Jane Urquhart, widow of Staats Long Morris, to James Morris, 1801, February 4; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      "The widow of Staats Long Morris writes of the death of her husband -- Staats Long Morris (1728-1800) was a brother of Lewis Morris, the Signer and a half brother of Gouverneur Morris. He entered the British Army in 1756 and attained the rank of General. He married the Dutchess of Gordon and was Governor of Quebec in 1797."
    - William Harcourt to Mr. Du Roveray, 1801, February 5; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      "William - Third Earl of Harcourt, 1743-1830. British Lieutenant Colonel. Promoted Colonel for his capture of Lee in his camp. Major General - 1782, General - 1796, Field Marshal - 1820."
    - Lafayette to Masson - His son George has made his "successful debut" - he was wounded twice in an action which his Regiment, the 11th Hussars took part. Speaks of improvements on his farm and his plans for improving the stock, 1801, February 6; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Nathaniel Pendleton - Legal paper, 1801, March 9; ADS (Box 3, Folder 1)
      "Hamilton's second in the Burr duel - Nathaniel Pendleton (1756-1821) entered the war when nineteen years old, was a Major on General Greene's staff and received the thanks of Congress for his gallantry at Eutaw. President Washington suggested his name for Secretary of State, but the appointment was opposed by Alexander Hamilton. They later became close personal friends. Pendleton was a delegate to the Constitutional Convention of 1787, but did not sign because of his absence on the last day."
    - Levi Lincoln to his wife - "The singing of the birds by a note I well understand, invites my return to Worcester" - the idea of the President is to permit the heads of Departments to visit their families, 1801, March 11; ADS (Box 3, Folder 1)
      "Levi Lincoln, who was Attorney General under President Jefferson, acted as Secretary of State until James Madison could arrive home and be sworn in as such Secretary."
    - Lafayette to Citizen Perregeaux, 1801, May 6; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Lagarde, Secretary of the Directory - Report on the confiscation of the property of an emigre, 1801, April 27; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Louis-Andre Pichon, 1801, June 21; ADS (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Francois Marie d'Aboville to "Chef de Brigade Directeur de l'Artillerie a Paris", 1801, June 21; ADS (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Louis Nicholas Pierre Joseph, Comte Dubois, Prefect of the Paris Police - Instructs the Committee of Three to investigate certain matters, 1801, August 16; ADS (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Jacques Necker to Messrs. LeRoy, Bayard & Evarts - Regarding land in New York, 1801, August 31; ADS 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Manifest of Sloop "Caroline" at New London, 1801, October 1; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 1)
      "The Brigadier General who served at the court martial of General Charles Lee, Jedidiah Huntington (1743-1818) - Huntington was born in Connecticut; graduated at Harvard, class of 1763; belonged to the Sons of Liberty; was a member of the Connecticut Committee on Correspondence; raised a company, of which he was made Captain and with his troops joined the Army at Cambridge in April 1775. Huntington was not only a member of the Court that tried General Charles Lee, but was also one of the Court that examined Major Andre in September 1780. President Washington appointed him Collector of Customs at New London, in which post he served 26 years. Huntington's first wife was a daughter of Governor Trumbull and his second wife a sister of Bishop Moore of Virginia. At his home in Conencticut he was often host to our distinguished Allies, among his guests being Lafayette, Von Steuben and Pulaski. Huntington was one of the committee of four that drafted the Constitution of the Society of Cincinnati, in 1783."
    - Jean Victor Moreau - Testimonials for citizen Albert's conduct in the Army of the Rhine, 1801, October 18; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      "Jean Victor Moreau (1761-1813) studied law, but in the Revolution commanded the volunteers from Rennes and was made a General of Division in 1794. Appointed in 1796 to the chief command on the Rhine and Moselle, defeated the Archduke Charles at Ettlingen and drove the Austrians back to the Danube. He was then deprived of his command, but in 1798 was made head of the Army in Italy. The party of Sieyes which overthrew the Directory, offered him the dictatorship; he declined it, but lent his assistance to Bonaparte on the 18th Brumaire. In 1800 he won from the Austrians at Hohenlinden. Napoleon, grown very jealous of Moreau, accused him of plotting, and he was sentenced to two years' imprisonment (1804), but it was commuted to banishment and Moreau settled in New Jersey, U.S.A. In 1813 he joined the Emperor of Russia and marched against Dresden, where both his legs were broken by a French cannon bal and he died after amputation. He is buried in St. Petersburg, Russia."
    - French Consul at Norfolk (Oster) to Governor James Monroe, 1801, November 6; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - De Rochambeau to Adjutant-Commander Coussand, 1801, November 18; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to James McHenry - Tells of visiting Napoleon, 1801, November 22; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Edward Hand to Messrs. Simon and H. Gratz, 1801, December 30; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Napoleon - He is thankful that "Citizen General" will do something about the return of Lafayette's maps, 1802, January 10; ADS (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - La Fond (French Naval Captain) to Admiral Bruix - Describing the French Fleet taht is about to sail for the West Indies. In giving his Admiral the news of the day he says "It is said that the negroes have revolted at Guadeloupe and that General Lacrosse has been massacred", 1802, January 13; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Official correspondence covering the investigation ordered by Congress of the accounts of Jefferson while Secretary of State, with particular reference to the Lafayette fund, 1802, March 6; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      "NOTE - This document evidences that the acute political situation of that day had inspired the enemies in Congress, of Thomas Jefferson to proe into the financial accounts of Jefferson when he was Secretary of State, and especially as to his advances in the aid of Lafayette."
    - Enclosed with Albert Gallatin to Joseph Nicholson - Joseph Nourse's investigation into Thomas Jefferson's finances, 1802, March 11 (Ovflat 30)
    - Mme Lafayette to Gouverneur Morris - On the family debts and their desire to settle it honorably, 1802, May 27; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - License for Jacques Christoph Germain, "citizen of the French Republic," to live in London - Signed by John King, 1802, May 31; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes handwritten translation into French
      Also includes transcription
    - Alured Clarke, General, and William Stevens, Lieut. General, concerning the "Taubert Fensibles" commanded by Col. Sir Edward Leslie, 1802, June 3; ADS (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Gouverneur Morris to Mme. Lafayette - His answer to her suggestions, 1802, August 16; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Richard Peters, member of the Board of War - Signed memo, 1802, August 23; ADS (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette to James McHenry - It has been intimated that the United States Congress may do something financial for his benefit, 1802, October 10; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes transcription
    - Ebenezer Elmer to George Burgin, 1802, October 23; ADS (Box 3, Folder 2)
      "Dr. Ebenezer Elmer (1752-1843), a native of Bridgeton, N.J., was surgeon of the 2nd N.J. Regiment in 1777. After the war he filled many important civic positions during his long life. Again in the War of 1812 he served in a New Jersey Brigade."
    - Matilda Stoughton de Jaudenes to her father, 1802, October 27; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Mme Lafayette to Morris - On family debt and its payment, 1802, December 10; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - James Monroe to James Madison - The bearer of the letter was captain Debutts under whose command Monroe had sailed to France, 1802, December 17; ADS (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bill of Exchange for £323.9.4 drawn by David Humphreys on John Trumbull at London - Accepted by the signature of Trumbull, 1802, December 20; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 2)
      "George Washington's military secretary, David Humphreys, 1753-1818"
    - Jared Ingersoll to Frederick Smith, 1802, December 22; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      "Jared Ingersoll (1749-1822) was of a Connecticut family but settled and practised law in Philadelphia. He made the acquaintance of Benjamin Franklin in Paris and on his return advocated the Revolution, although he was a son of the loyalist Jared Ingersoll, a Stamp Agent for the Crown. The son was a member of the Continental Congress and of the Constitutional Convention. In 1812 he was the unsuccessful candidate of the Federal Party for the Vice Presidency."
    - Unknown signed note, 1802, December 27; ADS (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes partial transcription
    - Brig. General Henry Lee (Light Horse Harry) to Mr. Griffith - "My detention here is serious beyond words", 1802, December; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      "Henry Lee wrote this letter at a time when he was 'confined' in Pennsylvania because of his pecuniary embarrassments, due largely to his extravagant hospitality. The biographies say he was not permitted to leave the County of Spottsylvania, in Pennsylvania, but they are silent as to whether he was actually in prison, for debt."
    - Lafayette to d'Arblay - He is sorry to learn from Princess d'Hennin that d'Arblay cannot visit La Grange as his proscription has not been raised and he must go to England. d'Arblay had been one of Lafayette's aides-de-camp and was imprisoned at Antwerp. After he joined the other emigres in England he married Fannie Burney, the writer, who later visited with the Lafayette family at La Grange, 1803, January 17; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Also includes notes about contents and context
    - Mathieu Dumas to "Colonel", 1803, January 31; ADS (Box 3, Folder 3)
      "Dumas once wrote - 'Above all I had heartily espoused the cause of the independence of the Americas and I should have felt extreme regret at losing the honor of combating for their liberty.'" "A leader of the grenadiers - Count Mathieu Dumas (1753-1837) came over with Rochambeau as an aide-de-camp and served throughout the campaign. In the French Revolution he aided Lafayette in the formation of the National Guard, but became an emigre during the Terror. He took part in the Revolution of 1830 and was made a Peer of France in 1831."
    - Henry Lee to Messrs. Nicklin & Griffith, 1803, February 4; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Regarding the last will and testament of John Pingree Williams of New Hampshire - Signed by N. Emery, J. Melcher, Ebenezer French, Benjamin Woods, Edward Sherburne, and Josiah Adams, 1803, March 8; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Pougens - "Here I am upon a hard bed to the foot of which my leg is tied and to the end I am fastened by a belt", 1803, March 29; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      "NOTE - Lafayette's signature indicates that it was difficult for him to write."
    - Lafayette to McHenry - News of his broken thigh, 1803, March 30; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Francois Marquis de Barthelemy to ?, 1803, May 14; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 3, Folder 3)
      "Francois Marquis de Barthelemy, French Statesman (1747-1830) - Royalist sympathizer - deported to Guiana - successively in the favor of Napoleon and Louis XVIII."
    - Lafayette to James McHenry - Description of the treatment of his thigh injury, which ahs turned out so badly, 1803, June 1; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Minister James Monroe - Offers his affectionate congratulations on Monroe's appointment to the London Embassy. Lafayette's leg has not yet healed and the surgeons tell him he should not think of attempting to go to Paris, nothing else could have prevented "my joining our American fellow citizens on the patriotic occasion" (July 4th Dinner), 1803, July 3; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to James Madison - Saying that he has written to the President expressing his gratitude for the bountiful, flattering grant of land with which he has been honored by Congress (in Louisiana), 1803, July 7; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Fulwar Skipwith, the United States Government business agent at Paris, 1803, July 9; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Power of Attorney signed by Lafayette - But running to blank-covering warrants, exchangeable for 11,525 acres public land north of Ohio River, and above the mouth of the Kentucky River, 1803, July 9; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Enclosure to Fulwar Skipwith letter of same date
    - Lafayette to Thomas Sumter, son of his fellow officer, General Sumter - His American friends get news of his accident, 1803, July 13; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - J. B. Boucheseiche to Dubois, Prefect of Police - Recommending extra security at the opening of a new tragedy at the Theatre Francais, 1803, July 23; ADS (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Charles James Fox to his brother, 1803, July 29; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      "Charles James Fox (1749-1806) was the third son of the first Lord Holland. In his early days in Parliament he supported Lord North, but during the American Revolution Fox was the formidable opponent of the coercive policies of the Government. After the downfall of North, Pitt came into power and Fox was his active foe, but at Pitt's death in 1806 Fox was recalled to office."
    - James Henry Craig to Robert Brownrigg, 1803, September 14; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to LaCoste - He thinks he will again have complete control of his legs, 1803, September 24; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Masson - He is still suffering from the effects of his accident. "My entire family has been re-united around me, my wife, the three young families and my three granddaughters", 1803, October 15; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to James Monroe - Tells of having written letters of thanks to President Jefferson, Madison and Gallatin, 1803, December 3; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Skipwith, 1803, December 29; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - John Brown to Aaron Burr - Declining his dinner invitation, 1804, January 2; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Jean-Xavier Bureau de Pusy to "Citoyen Ministre", 1804, March 15; ADS (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Gunning Bedford, Jr. - Check for $300, 1804, April 9; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 3, Folder 4)
      "Gunning Beford, Jr. (1747-1812) was a cousin of Gunning Bedford (1730-1797) who was the patriot Governor of Delaware. For a time Gunning Bedford, Jr. was an aide to George Washington. In the Constitutional Convention his eloquence and logic had much to do with influencing the decision to give equal representation in the Senate to the large and small States."
    - Check for $20 - Signed by unknown, 1804, April 12; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed, on scrapbook page (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Power of Attorney for WIlliam Balfour - Signed by William Bryant and Morris King, 1804, August 14 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Jonathan Dayton to Jacob Burnet and James Findley, Cincinnati, Ohio - Introducing Rev. William Stoughton, who is settling in the West, 1804, August 23; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      "Jonathan Dayton (1760-1824), son of Major General Elias Dayton, was Paymaster in his father's Regiment, the 3rd New Jersey. At Yorktown young Dayton served under Lafayette. Dayton was in Congress many terms, being Speaker of the House twice. He was United States Senator 1799-1805. He was arrested for alleged conspiracy with Burr, but was never tried."
    - Receipt of payment - Signed by George Reid and Timothy Walker, 1804, August; ADS (Box 3, Folder 4)
      "George Reid (1733-1815) was born in Londonderry, N.H. He became captain of a company of minute-men in 1775 and on receiving the news of the Battle of Lexington, joined General Stark's regiment at Mdeford and took an honorable part at Bunker Hill. In November 1775 he was appointed Lieutenant-Colonel of the 2nd New Hampshire Regiment, served as Colonel after the capture of Nathan Hale, took part in the Battle of Bemis Heights in October 1777, was present at the surrender of Burgoyne, and later in the surrender of Cornwallis. He was elected Sheriff of Rockingham County, N.H. in 1791. Timothy Walker (1737-1822), active New Hampshire patriot, member of its first House of Representatives in 1776, and a member of its Committee of Safety. In 1777 became Justice of the Court of Common Pleas for Rockingham County and held the office twenty-three years."
    - Lafayette agrees to pay to Pierre Maury, a Guard of Chavaniac, an annual pension of seventy five francs for life, 1804, September 9; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Duke of Northumberland to "Sir", 1804, September 16; ADS (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Archenholz, 1800, September 20; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - John Wilkes to Mr. Swinburne, appended to a letter from George Lackington, 1800, September 24; ADS (Box 3, Folder 4)
      "Brand Whitock says, 'In London, Beaumarchais became thick as thieves with John Wilkes, the demagogue, who convinced him that England was on the brink of a revolution,' and states that Beaumarchais met Arthur Lee through Wilkes, "the radical demagaogue, who was storming the House of Commons with a mob at his heels, and sending shivers down the backs of the Tories and City Members.""
    - Lafayette's Power of Attorney to James Madison, 1804, October 9; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      "Lafayette gave Madison a Power of Attorney to deal with the land grant from Congress"
    - Lafayette to Madison - Long letter on many subjects - "You know that the storms of the French Revolution have washed off the almost totality of my fortune", 1804, October 10; Photostat 5 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Consignee's Oath - Signed by Ebenezer Stevens (Col.), 1804, October 13; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Joseph Fouche to John Armstrong - Regarding the status of M. Booth and M. Drummond, 1804, October 20; ADS (Box 3, Folder 4)
      "Joseph Fouche, Duke of Otranto (1763-1820), hailed the Revolution with delight, in the Convention of 1792 voted for the execution of Louis and his commission to castigate Lyons (1794) was marked with great cruelty. In 1794 he was expelled from the Convention as a Terrorist, yet in September 1799 he was made Minister of Police, which post he held off and on for many years. He died in exile in 1820. He was unscrupulous, politic and sagatious and made an admirable head of Police."
    - Lafayette to (?) - Mr. Pitre (?) a New York merchant is in Paris and is to consult with Lafaytte and Mr. Baring, the banker, on the Louisiana lands, 1804, October; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Skipwith, 1804, November 10; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Fulwar Skipwith - He has made powers of attorney to James Madison and Francis Huger, 1804, November 19; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Minister James Monroe - He requests Monroe's help in certain changes in the French-Spanish Treaty concerning merinos, in the raising of which he is interested, 1804, December 6; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Samuel Otis, Secretary to John Harvie, James Pleasants and Meriweather Jones - A Summons to appear and testify before the U.S. Senate in the Impeachment PRoceedings against Samuel Chase, Associate Justice of the Supreme Court, 1804, December 24; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Bollman to Lafayette, 1804, December 25; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to President Jefferson - His wife's health is still affected by her sufferings in the Olmutz prison - A five page letter on the politics of Europe, 1804, October 8; Photostat 7 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Enclosed with Jefferson to Madison, 1804
    - Lafayette to Henry Dearborn - Respecting the grant of land - "I am proud to acknowledge that in my present circumstances and those of my family, the bounty of Congress has been peculiarly seasonable", 1804; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Christopher Greenup to Governor of Tennessee - Enclosing two Resolutions, 1805, January 2; Printed document signed (Box 3, Folder 5)
      "Christopher Greenup (1750-1818) served throughout the Revolution, attained the rank of Colonel and at the close of the war settled in Frankfort, in Kentucky, then known as the "dark and bloody ground." He practised law there, served in Congress from 1791 to 1797 and was Governor of Kentucky from 1804 to 1808."
    - Lafayette to Skipwith, 1805, January 15; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Pierre Francois Charles Augereau to General Donzelos, 1805, January 23; ADS (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Jefferson and Madison signed permission slips (official ship papers), 1805, February 1 (Ovflat 30)
    - Lafayette to Skipwith, 1805, March 11; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Benjamin Lincoln, Collector of the Port - Signature on a "Certificate of Importation" for the "Doak", 1805, April 8; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 5)